A Guide to the Barnum, Richardson Company Records 1980.0037
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Barnum, Richardson Company Records
undated, 1793-1925
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1980.0037
12.75 Linear Feet
Barnum, Richardson Company was established in 1830 in Salisbury, CT. The company was based on a foundry that remelt pig iron. Barnum, Richardson and Company, as it was first called, was a small firm specializing in the production of clock and sash weights, plow castings, and other small items. In the 1860s there were several reorganizations and name changes. The company merged and expanded into the turn of the century and was purchased in 1920 by the Salisbury Iron Company. The Salisbury Iron Company went out of business in 1923 and shut down what was then the last of Connecticut's iron furnaces.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The combined records of Malcolm D. Rudd and the Barnum Richardson Company were donated by Yale University Library to the Historical Manuscripts and Archives Division (now Archives & Special Collections) of the University Of Connecticut Libraries in January, 1980.
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence (1882-1926)
Series II: Companies (1854-1918)
Series III: Administrative Records (1833-1925)
Series IV: Labor Records (undated, 1887-1889)
Series V: Production Records (undated, 1879-1916)
Series VI: General Accounts (1841-1917)
Series VII: Merger Companies (1831-1856)
Series VIII: Estate of William H. Barnum (1793-1919)
History
Barnum, Richardson Company was established in 1830 by Milo Barnum and his son-in-law, Leonard Richardson in Salisbury, CT. Barnum was born in Dutchess County, New York, in 1790 and moved to Lime Rock in Salisbury, CT, in 1820 to engage in business as a merchant. The town of Salisbury was well known, at that time, for its extensive iron bed and for the exceptional quality of its iron ore. The company was based on a foundry that remelt pig iron. Barnum, Richardson and Company, as it was first called, was a small firm specializing in the production of clock and sash weights, plow castings, and other small items.
In 1840, Barnum's son, William, joined the company and the firm expanded to include production of hardware for the new railroad industry. The company's first major products were chains, frogs and headblocks for the Boston and Albany Railroad, which had just begun construction.
Salisbury iron proved most valuable in the manufacture of railroad car wheels. The iron did not break easily under tension and it was almost impervious to extremes of heat and cold. Barnum, Richardson and Company prospered because of the increasing demand for this high quality iron, and owned a number of the town's manufacturing concerns and most of its housing.
In 1852, Milo Barnum retired from active service and the name of the company was changed to Richardson, Barnum and Company. In 1858, the company purchased the Beckley furnace in East Canaan, and in 1862, obtained the Forbes furnace in the same town. At about the same time, the company purchased another foundry in Chicago. The company was reorganized as a joint stock company and renamed the Barnum and Richardson Manufacturing Company. In 1864, Leonard Richardson died, and the company was reorganized again as the Barnum, Richardson Company, a joint stock company with William H. Barnum as president and general manager. The heirs of Leonard Richardson continued to maintain an interest in the company.
A second foundry was built in Salisbury in 1870 and a third furnace in East Canaan in 1872. A new wheel foundry was built in Chicago in 1873. In 1870, the Salisbury foundries produced 10,000 car wheels. The foundries in Chicago had a capacity of three hundred car wheels per day. By 1881, the company owned eight blast furnaces in the Salisbury are which used an average of twelve hundred bushels of charcoal per day and produced eleven tons of iron to each furnace per day. The company also owned and operated its own mine, the Ore Hill mine, which in the late 1880s was providing 20,000 tons of ore per year.
Barnum, Richardson merged with several small companies during its history including: Landon, Moore and Company; S. B. Moore & Company; Sterling, Chapin & Company; and Sterling & Moore Company. Subsidiaries of Barnum, Richardson included Hunts-Lyman Iron Company, Lime Rock Iron Company, Sharon Valley Iron Company, Cornwall Bridge Iron Company and Millerton Iron Company. Companies affiliated with Barnum, Richardson included Brook Pit Mining Company, Forbes Ore-Bed Company, David Digging Company, Adams-Chatfield Company and Chatfield Mining Company.
In 1889, William Barnum died after a long and exceptional career as an industrialist. By the early twentieth century, the Salisbury iron industry was in decline. The newly imported Bessemer steel process, which produced a product more adaptable than the iron produced in small quantities by Barnum, Richardson made the small furnace iron industry of Connecticut obsolete. In 1920, Barnum, Richardson Company was purchased by the Salisbury Iron Company. This new firm went out of business in 1923 and shut down what was then the last of Connecticut's iron furnaces.
Custodial History
Records of the Barnum, Richardson Company were donated to Harvard University, the School of Business Administration, by Alfred B. Stone. Stone had purchased the company property after the business had ceased operation. Harvard University transferred the collection to the Yale University Library, which later received a donation from the estate of Malcolm D. Rudd. The Rudd papers contain records of the smaller iron companies which merged with the Barnum, Richardson Company.
Scope and Content
The collection contains and broad range of materials documenting the manufacture of iron in Connecticut including correspondence, financial and administrative records, minutes, employee materials, blueprints and patterns for factory equipment, production records, and documents pertaining to companies that merged with the Barnum, Richardson Company.
Iron foundries; Decedents' estates; Inventories; Salisbury (inhabited place); Iron industry and trade; Connecticut (state); Financial Records; Real property; Administrative records; Deeds; Blueprints (reprographic copies).; Stock certificates; Correspondence; Lime Rock (inhabited place); Salisbury Iron Company; Richardson, Leonard, -1864; Barnum, Milo, 1790-
- Series I: Correspondence, 1882-1916
  - A, 1883-1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B. F. Sturtevant Company, 1906-1913 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Barr, J. N., Esquire, 1900-1901 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bal - Bar, 1893-1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Britton Company, 1914-1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Brown Car Wheel Works, 1902-1916 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brad - Bux, 1900-1916 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Buffalo Car Wheel Foundry Company, 1901-1913 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - C, 1885-1916 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chicago, Milwaukee & St. Paul Railway Company, 1894-1910 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chilled Roll Foundry, 1897-1899 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Commerce, Department of, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - D, 1900-1916 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Douglas, George B., 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - E, 1884-1916 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - F, 1889-1916 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - G, 1899-1916 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Gartshore, John J., 1889 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - General Brake Shoes, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Globe Elevator Company, 1913-1916 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - W. R. Grace & Company, 1912-1916 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Griffin Wheel Company, 1902-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Haas - Hapgoods, 1898-1907 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hardis - Harvey, 1880-1914 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Hascall - Hurlburt, 1876-1915 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Harbison-Walker Company, 1899-1906 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Hartford Steam Boiler Inspection & Insurance Company, 1900-1916 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Hastings Pavement Company, 1908-1916 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Henshaw, J. O., 1914-1916 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - I, 1882, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - J, 1899-1902 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - K, 1898-1902 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Keystone Carriage Company, 1900-1901 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - L, 1898-1916 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - M, 1871-1916 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Manufacturer's Charcoal Company, 1914-1916 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - F. W. Marshall & Company, 1900-1916 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - McConihe, Isaac, 1878-1886 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - McKee, Fuller & Company, 1901-1902 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - N, 1883-1916 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - National Iron Bank, 1883-1890 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Company, 1906-1916 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - O, 1900-1916 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Osgood Bradley Car Company, 1909-1916 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - P, 1900-1916 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Pennsylvania Car Wheel Company, 1900-1902 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Pittsburgh Forge & Iron Company, 1914-1915 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Postcards, 1890-1909 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Pratt & Whitney Company, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - R, 1897-1912 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Reeder, Lewis R., 1901-1903 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Rex Buggy Company, 1900-1903 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Richland Vehicle Company, 1900-1903 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Rochester Wheel Company, 1899-1901 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Rodebaugh, G. H., 1900-1901 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Russell Wagons, 1902-1903 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Safety - Seffel, 1900-1914 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Shay - Sprout, 1900-1916 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Stafford - Sylvester, 1899-1916 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Seeman Carriage Company, 1901-1902 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Sheffield-King Milling Company, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Shortsville Wheel Company, 1899-1901 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Simpson, Thacher & Barnum (William H.), 1884-1914 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - E. W. Spurr Company, 1902-1914 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Standard Charcoal Company, 1909-1913 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Stanley Works, 1905-1916 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Syracuse Chilled Plow Company, 1904-1908 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - T, 1897-1916 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - U, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Varnish, 1899-1901 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Wachenfeld - Western Union, 1897-1916 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Westinghouse - Wright, 1905-1916 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - R.J. Waddell & Company, 1912-1914 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Warner & Landon, 1893-1916 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Wason Manufacturing Company, 1892-1908 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Whitehead Brothers and Company, 1905-1917 (Box 4, Folder 76, Folder 77)
  - Wilson & Eaton, 1905-1916 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Y, 1912-1913 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Z, 1907-1912 (Box 4, Folder 80)
- Series II: Companies, 1854-1918
  - American Mining Company, 1869-1870 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Barnard Hardware Company, 1854-1890 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Brook Pit Mining Company, 1881-1890 (Box 5, Folder 83-85)
  - Cambria Mining Company, 1884-1897 (Box 5, Folder 86-89)
  - Car Trust, 1880 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Chatfield Mining Company, 1858-1896 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Cleveland Bridge and Car Works, 1882-1883 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Contracting Chill Company, 1895-1904 (Box 6, Folder 93-98)
  - Cornwall Bridge Iron Company, 1862-1891 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Delaware & Hudson Canal Company, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - Detroit & Lake Superior Iron Manufacturing Co., 1885 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Elkhart Car Works Company, 1882-1883 (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Forbes Iron Company, 1857-1865 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Gaylord Iron Company, 1889-1892 (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - Harvey Manufacturing Company, 1880-1886 (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - Holley Manufacturing Company, 1891 (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - Hudson Foundry & Machine Shop, 1872-1873 (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Hunts Lyman Iron Company, 1861-1889 (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Janney & Hien Coupler Company, 1887-1890 (Box 6, Folder 109)
  - D. Knowlton & Company, 1875-1886 (Box 6, Folder 110)
  - Lillie Mining Company, 1888-1897 (Box 6, Folder 111-112)
  - Lucy Mining Company, 1887-1895 (Box 6, Folder 113-115)
  - G. Menzel & Company, 1881-1882 (Box 7, Folder 116)
  - Millerton Iron Company, 1877-1909 (Box 7, Folder 117)
  - Nichols Land & Cattle Company, 1882-1898 (Box 7, Folder 118-132)
  - Old Hill Mine, 1913-1915 (Box 7, Folder 133-135)
  - Patent Axle & Box Foundry Company, 1891 (Box 8, Folder 136)
  - Pine Lake Iron Company, 1888-1890 (Box 8, Folder 137)
  - Pomeroy Mining Company, 1896-1898 (Box 8, Folder 138)
  - Richmond Iron Works, 1868-1908 (Box 8, Folder 139-140)
  - Riga Mining Company, 1885-1889 (Box 8, Folder 141)
  - Rochester Car Wheel Works, 1882-1884 (Box 8, Folder 142-143)
  - Sputyen Duyvil Rolling Mill Company, 1868-1869 (Box 8, Folder 144)
  - Suspension Car Truck Company, 1886-1890 (Box 8, Folder 145)
  - Valparaiso Wheel, 1872-1883 (Box 8, Folder 146)
  - Washburn Car Wheel Company, 1890-1897 (Box 8, Folder 147)
  - Washburn Hunts & Company, 1890-1897 (Box 8, Folder 148)
  - Weed Mine, 1914-1918 (Box 8, Folder 149-151)
- Series III: Administrative Records, 1833-1925
  - Agreements, 1863-1925 (Box 9, Folder 152)
  - Alabama & Tennessee River Railroad Company, 1854 (Box 9, Folder 153)
  - Assignments of patent, J. H. Congdon, 1882-1883 (Box 9, Folder 154)
  - Bill of sale, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 155)
  - Blank forms, undated (Box 9, Folder 156)
  - Board of Directors, Articles of Association, 1864-1913 (Box 9, Folder 157)
  - Boyd's City Dispatch, undated (Box 9, Folder 158)
  - Chicago & Canada Southern Railway Company bonds, 1890 (Box 9, Folder 159)
  - Duplicates and miscellaneous, undated (Box 9, Folder 160)
  - Estates
    - Hiram Bundy, 1883 (Box 9, Folder 161)
    - David S. Draper, 1887-1888 (Box 9, Folder 162)
    - Leonard Richardson, 1860-1888 (Box 9, Folder 163)
    - Frederick A. Walton, 1860-1892 (Box 9, Folder 164-165)
    - William F. Walton, 1869-1870 (Box 9, Folder 166)
  - Fire Insurance policy, 1890 (Box 9, Folder 167)
  - Grain market reports, 1883 (Box 9, Folder 168)
  - Insurance, 1886-1890 (Box 9, Folder 169)
  - Land transactions, 1854-1925 (Box 9, Folder 170-172)
  - Lord, Newman, 1870, 1877 (Box 10, Folder 173)
  - Notes protested, 1856-1890 (Box 10, Folder 174)
  - Notices of annual meetings, 1884-1889 (Box 10, Folder 175)
  - Notices of dividends, 1880-1889 (Box 10, Folder 176)
  - Page Farm, Martin McCarthy papers, Tompkins Farm Nelson McArthur land, Chatfield Mining Co., 1872-1886 (Box 10, Folder 177)
  - Patents—letters, assignments, 1864-1893 (Box 10, Folder 178)
  - Probate records, 1799-1811 (Box 10, Folder 179)
  - Production forms, 1915-1916 (Box 10, Folder 180)
  - Promissory note, 1833-1893 (Box 10, Folder 181)
  - Real estate, 1886-1892 (Box 10, Folder 182)
  - Report—Cornwall Bridge Iron Company, 1893 (Box 10, Folder 183)
  - Stock shares, 1852-1903 (Box 10, Folder 184)
  - Taxes, 1842-1894 (Box 10, Folder 185)
  - Walton deeds, 1832-1833 (Box 10, Folder 186)
  - Welch & Barnum, 1879-1883 (Box 10, Folder 187)
- Series IV: Labor Records, undated, 1887-1889
  - Weekly payroll sheets/ledgers
    - 1887 May - August (Box 11, Folder 188)
    - 1887 September - December (Box 11, Folder 189)
    - 1888 January - June (Box 11, Folder 190)
    - 1888-1889 July - March (Box 11, Folder 191)
  - Employee relations, undated (Box 11, Folder 192)
- Series V: Production Records, undated, 1879-1916
  - Blueprints and patterns, undated (Box 12, Folder 193)
  - Daily labor log, 1888 (Box 12, Folder 194)
  - Daily labor log, 1889 (Box 12, Folder 195-198)
  - Daily labor log, 1890 (Box 12, Folder 199-201)
  - Inventory, 1879-1916 (Box 12, Folder 202)
  - Lumber and timber inventory, 1910-1913 (Box 12, Folder 203)
  - Sample production receipts, 1913-1914 (Box 12, Folder 204)
  - Old Hill ore transportation/production, 1832-1834 (Oversize 1)
- Series VI: General Accounts, 1841-1920
  - Accounts receivable, 1908 (Box 13, Folder 205)
  - Accounts receivable, Town of Salisbury, 1915 (Box 13, Folder 206)
  - Accounts, statements of, 1888, 1893 (Box 13, Folder 207)
  - Accounts, sundry, 1871-1889 (Box 13, Folder 208)
  - Balance sheets, treasurer's reports, profits/loss sheets, 1869-1893 (Box 13, Folder 209)
  - Bank accounts, 1881-1902 (Box 13, Folder 210)
  - Bank drafts, 1876-1901 (Box 13, Folder 211)
  - Bids and proposals, 1915-1916 (Box 13, Folder 212)
  - Bills, 1841-1917 (Box 13, Folder 213)
  - Bills of lading, 1902-1916 (Box 13, Folder 214)
  - Blotters, 1916 (Box 13, Folder 215)
  - Bonds, 1873, 1885 (Box 13, Folder 216)
  - Chicago, Milwaukee and St. Paul Railway, 1882-1886 (Box 13, Folder 217)
  - Connecticut Power Company, 1915-1916 (Box 13, Folder 218)
  - Contracts, 1911-1916 (Box 13, Folder 219)
  - Credit memoranda, 1861-1916 (Box 13, Folder 220)
  - Davis Digging Company, 1837-1897 (Box 13, Folder 221-223)
  - Davis Digging Company, 1837-1897 (Oversize 1)
  - Forbes Ore Bed Company, 1854-1911 (Box 14, Folder 224-225)
  - Foundry and machine shop, 1888-1889 (Box 14, Folder 226)
  - Freight bills, 1875-1916 (Box 14, Folder 227)
  - Freight receipts, 1886-1916 (Box 14, Folder 228)
  - Globe elevator: shipping orders, 1906, 1916 (Box 14, Folder 229)
  - Grist mill prices, 1907-1916 (Box 14, Folder 230)
  - Housatonic Railroad Company, 1869-1888 (Box 14, Folder 231)
  - Indenture—Wheeler/Spooner, Spuyten Duyvil property, 1891 (Box 14, Folder 232)
  - Invoices, 1914-1915 (Box 14, Folder 233)
  - Invoices, 1916 (Box 14, Folder 234)
  - Memoranda of notes discounted, 1887-1889 (Box 14, Folder 235)
  - Michigan Central Railroad Company, 1873-1874 (Box 14, Folder 236)
  - Notes paid, payable and receivable, 1849-1884 (Box 15, Folder 237)
  - Notes payable, 1888 (Box 15, Folder 238)
  - Orders, 1902-1917 (Box 15, Folder 239-240)
  - Osgood-Bradley invoices, 1910-1912 (Box 15, Folder 241)
  - Purchases, 1913-1916 (Box 15, Folder 242)
  - Receipted bills and accounts, 1879-1891 (Box 15, Folder 243)
  - Receipts, 1839-1916 (Box 15, Folder 244)
  - Receivership indenture, 1920 (Box 15, Folder 245)
  - Records of bonds, 1870-1882 (Box 15, Folder 246)
  - Rent receipts: Yale College, 1888 (Box 15, Folder 247)
  - Sales, 1892-1916 (Box 15, Folder 248)
  - Salisbury Iron Corporation, 1888-1925 (Box 15, Folder 249)
  - Telephone bills and correspondence, 1880-1912 (Box 15, Folder 250)
  - Tire Setting Machine Company—letters received, 1897-1898 (Box 15, Folder 251)
  - Union Pacific Railway Company shipments, 1881-1882 (Box 15, Folder 252)
  - Way-bill, 1886 (Box 15, Folder 253)
  - Wheels shipped, monthly account of, 1914-1915 (Box 15, Folder 254)
  - Wheels shipped, monthly account of, 1914-1915 (Oversize 1)
- Series VII: Merger Companies, 1827-1856
  - Landon Branch and Company—account book, 1837-1838 (Box 16, Folder 255)
  - Landon, Moore and Company, 1836-1841 (Box 16, Folder 256-277)
  - Landon, Moore and Company, 1842-1848 (Box 17, Folder 278-282)
  - S. B. Moore and Company, 1848-1856 (Box 17, Folder 283-290)
  - Sterling, Chapin and Company, 1827-1830 (Box 17, Folder 291-292)
  - Sterling, Chapin and Company, 1831-1843 (Box 18, Folder 293-301)
  - Sterling and Moore, 1844-1847 (Box 18, Folder 302-306)
- Series VIII: Estate of William H. Barnum, 1793-1919
  - Accounts, 1889-1901 (Box 19, Folder 307)
  - Clapp settlement, 1887-1890 (Box 19, Folder 308)
  - Drafts, 1887-1919 (Box 19, Folder 309)
  - Land records, 1881-1906 (Box 19, Folder 310)
  - Letters, 1893 (Box 19, Folder 311)
  - Promissory notes, 1870-1898 (Box 19, Folder 312)
  - Taxes, 1891-1900 (Box 19, Folder 313)
  - Telephone bills, 1919 (Box 19, Folder 314)
  - Vouchers, 1896-1900 (Box 19, Folder 315-320)
  - Wood lots—records, surveys, 1793-1890 (Box 19, Folder 321)